Ilias Chalkidis

NLP Researcher / Data Scientist

Ilias Chalkidis

Tritonos 120, 17562 Athens, Greece

+30-6942825565 ihalk@aueb.gr

Personal page: https://iliaschalkidis.github.io
https://iliaschalkidis.github.io

skype id: liakoskiddo

Skills

I am currently studying for a PhD under the title of "Deep Neural Networks for Information Mining from legal texts" at the Department of Informatics in Athens University of Business and Economics under the supervision of Prof. Ion Androutsopoulos and Nikolaos Aletras. In 2016, I finished my MSc degree in Computer Science specialized in Advanced Information Systems, while working as a research associate on legal knowledge representation. I expertise in legal textual data analysis (AI & Law). I am looking forward to enhance my qualifications / skills and understanding on data science through different approaches.

- Advanced Programming Skills (Python, Java, C/C++, Prolog etc.)
- Machine Learning background (Keras, Tensorflow, SciKit Learn, etc.)
- Web Dev. Frameworks know-how (Spring MVC, Spring REST)
- Advanced Semantic Web technologies background
- Teamwork player & Leadership skills on IT
- Ability to cooperate from distance (remotely)
- Experience working with Agile, don't like it though...
- Experience on high-level business meeting and presentations with top-tier clients (banks, insurance/consulting companies).

Experience

Cognitiv+ / Head of Data Science (NLP)

APRIL 2016 - SEPTEMBER 2019, LONDON

The work circle included various tasks relevant to document intelligence to support Cognitiv+ contract management platform. The ML-NLP solutions were based on advanced machine learning approaches, such as deep learning.

<u>Accomplishments</u>

- Orchestrating challenging annotation projects.
- Resolving Automated Contract Structure Identification using an ML pipeline.
- Deployment of state-of-the-art contract element extractors and sentence/paragraph classifiers.

National and Kapodistrian University of Athens / Research Associate (Semantic Web)

FEBRUARY 2015 - JANUARY 2017, ATHENS

I was working as a research assistant on MaDGIK group (http://www.madgik.di.uoa.gr/) and especially on the Semantic Web Technologies Lab under Prof. Manolis Koubarakis.

Accomplishments

- Model Greek Legislation with Semantic Web Technologies (OWL,RDFS)
- Implement Nomothesi@ RESTful API web platform (http://legislation.di.uoa.gr)
- Create Nomothesi@ parser (parsed over 5,000 acts)
- Enhance Nomothesi@ parser with Named Entity Recognizer for persons, organizations and places and full-text indexing

Education

- Athens University of Economics and Business / Doctor of Philosophy (PhD), Informatics

PENDING 2020, ATHENS

Serving as a Lab Assistant:

- Language Technology (MsC program) (2016 up-to-date)
- Human Computer Interaction (2016 up-to-date)
- DataBases (2016 up-to-date)

Also served as a supervisor on two (2) MSc theses:

- "Named Entity Recognition, Linking and Generation for Greek Legislation", I. Angelidis, (2018)
- "Legal Text Classification on Greek Legislation based on the Greek Legal Code", C. Papaloukas, (2019)

- National and Kapodistrian University of Athens / Master of Science (MSc), Advanced Information Systems

2016, ATHENS

Served as a Teaching Assistant on:

- Artificial intelligence (AI) (2015-2016, 2016-2017)
- Knowledge Technologies (2016-2017)
- Systems Analysis (Structured Analysis and Design, UML) (2015-2016)

Also served as a supervisor on two (2) graduate theses:

- "Nomothesi@ API Reengineering the Electronic Platform", P. Soursos, (2015)
- "News Articles Representation using BBC Ontologies", E. Giama, (2016)

- National and Kapodistrian University of Athens / Bachelor of Science (BSc), Informatics and Telecommunications

2014, ATHENS

Extra specialization (Former Curriculum): "Computer Systems & Applications" Extra specialization (Current Curriculum): "Data and knowledge management"

Publications

- → Neural Contract Element Extraction Revisited. Iias Chalkidis, Manos Fergadiotis, Prodromos Malakasiotis and Ion Androutsopoulos. In the Proceedings of the Document Intelligence Workshop of the 33rd Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2019), Vancouver, Canada December 14, 2019.
- → Large-Scale Multi-Label Text Classification on EU Legislation. Ilias Chalkidis, Manos Fergadiotis, Prodromos Malakasiotis and Ion Androutsopoulos. In the Proceedings of the 57th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2019) (Short Papers), Florence, Italy, July 28 August 2, 2019.
- → Neural Legal Judgment Prediction in English. Ilias Chalkidis, Ion Androutsopoulos and Nikolaos Aletras. In the Proceedings of the 57th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2019) (Short Papers), Florence, Italy, July 28 August 2, 2019.
- → Extreme Multi-Label Legal Text Classification: A case study in EU Legislation. Ilias Chalkidis, Manos Fergadiotis, Prodromos Malakasiotis, Nikolaos Aletras and Ion Androutsopoulos. In the Proceedings of the Workshop on Natural Legal Language Processing of the Annual Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL-HLT 2019), Minneapolis, USA, June 2-7, 2019.
- → Towards a Decentralized, Trusted, Intelligent and Linked Public Sector: A Report from the Greek Trenches. Themis Beris, Iosif Angelidis, Ilias Chalkidis, Charalampos Nikolau, Christos Papaloukas, Panagiotis Soursos and Manolis Koubarakis. In the Proceedings of the Workshop on Linked Data on the Web and its Relationship with Distributed Ledgers (LDOW/LDDL) of the Web Conference 2019, San Francisco, USA, May 13-17, 2019.
- → Named Entity Recognition, Linking and Generation for Greek Legislation. Iosif Angelidis, Ilias Chalkidis and Manolis Koubarakis. In the Proceedings of the 31st International Conference on Legal Knowledge and Information Systems (JURIX 2018), Groningen, The Netherlands, December 12-14, 2018.
- → Deep Learning in Law: Early Adaptation and Legal Word Embeddings
 Trained on Large Corpora. Ilias Chalkidis and Dimitrios Kampas. In Artificial
 Intelligence and Law, Volume 27:2, Pages 171–198, Springer, December 11,
 2018.
- → Obligation and Prohibition Extraction Using Hierarchical RNNs. Ilias Chalkidis, Ion Androutsopoulos and Achilleas Michos. In the Proceedings of the 56th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2018) (Short Papers), Melbourne, Australia, July 15-20, 2018. Pages 254-259.2018.
- → A Deep Learning Approach to Contract Element Extraction. Ilias Chalkidis and Ion Androutsopoulos. In the Proceedings of the 30th International Conference on Legal Knowledge and Information Systems (JURIX 2017), Luxembourg City, Luxembourg, December 13-15, 2017. 2017.
- → Extracting Contract Elements. Ilias Chalkidis, Ion Androutsopoulos and Achilleas Michos. In Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Law (ICAIL 2017), London, UK, June 12–16, 2017, Pages 19–28. 2017.
- → Modeling and Querying Greek Legislation using Semantic Web Technologies. Ilias Chalkidis, Charalampos Nikolaou, Panagiotis Soursos and Manolis Koubarakis.In the Proceedings of the 14th European Semantic Web Conference (ESWC 2017), Portorož, Slovenia, May 28 June 1, 2017. Pages 591–606. 2017.

Languages

- Greek (Native Speaker)
- English (Excellent)
- Spanish (Basic level)

Other Interests

- Travel all around the world, broaden my horizons (17 countries in Europe, Northern America and Australia, many more to come in the future)
- Promoting policies for the inclusion of under-represented groups (women, people of colour) in IT environments